Finding Aid of the More Than One Struggle Oral History Project Records, 1939-2004, bulk 1995-1996
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
- 1. Oral History Interviews, 1995-1996
  - Jones, Walter
    Walter Jones moved to Milwaukee in 1959 when he began working for the Milwaukee Star. In 1967 he began working for the Milwaukee Courier. He discusses why the Star got involved with education issues, his views on the Milwaukee United School Integration Committee boycotts of 1964 and 1965, the Black Power movement in Milwaukee starting in 1966 and 1967, and student involvement in the school movement.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 43-44)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Kenner, Peggy
    Peggy Kenner, former president of the Milwaukee Public School (MPS) Board and winner of the Wisconsin Women's Network Stateswomen of the Year, speaks to her work with the Peckham-Steuben Community Council to develop an integration plan, MPS' discriminatory transfer policy in the 1960's and early 1970's, the "Committee of 100", and her work with the MPS school board.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 45)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lucas, Reaber
    Reaber Lucas moved to Milwaukee in 1965 from Mississippi when she started working with the Organizations of Organizations (Triple O). She discusses her work with Triple O including working on Title 1, organizing the teacher's aides, their involvement with the North Division and Rufus King clusters and the racial make-up of the organization. She also gives her opinion on the school desegregation lawsuit, and growing up in segregated schools.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 46)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - McAlister, Mona
    Mona McAlister graduated from St. Benedict High School and sent her five children to St. Boniface School. She witnessed St. Boniface's transition from predominately white to predominately black. Her interview topics include St. Boniface's transition from a parochial school to a community school, the Federation of Independent Community Schools and the effect of white flight on the Milwaukee parochial schools.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 47)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - McKay, Pauline
    Pauline McKay moved to Milwaukee in 1950 from Lexington, MS. She discusses her work with North Division High School groups, her involvement with the site planning committee for the new North Division building, the Chapter 220 program, problems with busing, the desegregation plan of 1976, and growing up in segregated schools.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 48)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - McNeil, Rev. Joseph
    Reverend Joseph McNeil, a Milwaukee native, was active in education reform for African American children, and served as the chairman of the North Division Advisory Council in the 1970's. His interview topics include Title III and cluster schools, parent involvement with changes at North Division High School in the late 1960's early 1970's, Milwaukee's attempt to decentralize the school system, segregation at Tech High School, and dealing with Police Chief Harold Breier.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 49)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Murrell, Peter, Sr., and Eva Ruth
    Eva and Peter Murrell came to Milwaukee in the 1940's and became active in school issues through their children. They discuss We-Milwaukee, Eva's work with the Parent Teacher Association from 1962-1966, problems with the Milwaukee schools their children attended, busing, the desegregation decisions of 1976 and 1979, and African American immersion schools.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 50)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Nicholas, Clarence P.
    Clarence P. Nicholas came to Milwaukee in 1970 to teach in the Milwaukee Public School system where he taught for 36 years and was the spokesman for the Black Teacher's Caucus (BTC) in 1977. Interview topics include the activities and members of the BTC, friction between BTC and the Milwaukee Teachers' Education Association (MTEA), and BTC's interaction with key activists such as Lloyd Barbee.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 51)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Pitts, Cynthia Bryant
    Cynthia Pitts came to Milwaukee in 1965 and worked with the Inner City Development Project. She discusses growing up in segregated Baltimore, her role with the Inner City Development Project, school issues, student protests, and the goals of the United Community Action Committee.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 52)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Robertson, Helen
    Helen Robertson came to Milwaukee in 1970 to teach after attending UW-Madison. Her interview topics include the quality of education in Milwaukee's independent community school movement in the 1970's, Milwaukee magnet and Montessori schools, the Coalition to Save North Division High School and the Governor's Commission on Better Quality of Schools.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 53)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Robinson, Jeanetta
    Jeanetta Robinson came to Milwaukee in 1957 and participated in many civil rights groups in Milwaukee. She discusses her work with Congress of Racial Equality, the Freedom School boycott of 1964, the Poverty Advisory Council, organizing student walkouts, her children's school experience, the difference between integrated and quality education, and her work with the Triple O-sponsored Two-Way or No-Way busing protest of 1979-1980.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 54)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rogers, Tazaleen, and Theodora Cecelia Rogers
    Tazzaleen Rogers, interviewed with her daughter Theodora Cecelia Rogers, discusses working with Milwaukee United School Integration Committee and the Coalition to Save North Division High School. She was also president of 12th Street School PTA. Her interview topics include her children's experience as the first group of African Americans to attend Shorewood and South Division High Schools and her involvement, in general, with the Milwaukee civil rights movement.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 55)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Saunders, Lawrence, and Kathleen Saunders
    Larry Saunders came to Milwaukee to attend Marquette University where he met Kathleen. They discuss working for the Milwaukee Globe and the Milwaukee Star, the hatred in Milwaukee for African Americans, and the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom which Larry participated in.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 56)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Savage, Rochelle, and Roosevelt Savage
    Rochelle Savage and her husband, Roosevelt, were involved with Milwaukee United School Integration Committee in 1965. Their interview topics include intact busing at Garden Homes School, communicating and information in the education reform movement, Father Groppi and the Commandos, and Lloyd Barbee and the school desegregation lawsuit. They also discuss the concept of improving neighborhood schools instead of integration, and the removal of strong African American teachers from the inner-city schools.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 57)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Scott, Wesley L.
    Wesley L. Scott was the CEO of the Milwaukee Urban League and an active member of We-Milwaukee. He discusses Milwaukee civil rights in the 1950's, his activities with the Urban League, criticism of newspaper coverage of the school movement, the goals of We-Milwaukee, efforts to support black history, and the role of civil rights groups in the 1970's desegregation fight.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 58)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Seefeldt, Flora B.
    Flora Seefeldt came to Milwaukee in 1958 and was appointed by President Johnson to serve as a member of the educational board for Counselor Finch, then United States Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare. Her interview topics include the United Community Action Group, her children's experience with intact busing from McKinley School to Garden Homes School, and the poor quality of Milwaukee schools in the black community including lack of books and supplies.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 59-60)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Smith, Michael C.
    Michael Smith came to Milwaukee in 1972 to teach at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. He discusses his involvement with Organization of Organizations (Triple O) in 1974-1975, his children's school experience in 1976, problems with the Milwaukee Public School System's Chapter 220 program, goals of the Concerned Citizens for Quality Education, his work with the Governor's Commission on Quality Education, and the fight over the North Division District in the early 1990's.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 61)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Spencer, Anita K.
    Anita Spencer, a Milwaukee native, attended Ninth Street School, McKinley Elementary, West Division and Lincoln High Schools. Her interview topics include her membership with local organizations such as the United Black Community Council, Project Respect and Two-Way or No-Way. Spencer also talks about overcrowding in Auer Elementary school and how intact busing affected her family.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 62)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Swan, Monroe
    Monroe Swan came to Milwaukee in 1955 and was elected state senator in 1972. He discusses his involvement with Organization of Organizations (Triple O), which he joined in 1967, his integration stance as senator, his role in Blac-A-Vention, a 1974 meeting of inner-city activists, problems with the Chapter 220 program, the 1976 desegregation decision, goals of the Two-Way or No-Way busing protest, and the reform movements of 1989.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 63-64)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Todd, Leon
    Leon Todd was elected to the Milwaukee Public School (MPS) Board in 1975. His interview topics include his strategy for becoming one of the first blacks elected to the MPS Board and his alliance with the German-American societies in Milwaukee which resulted in the development of Milwaukee's integrated language immersion schools. He also talks about the Chapter 220 voluntary integration program, magnet schools, and the Coalition to Save North Division High School.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 65)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Verdin, Brian
    Brian Verdin is a Milwaukee native and graduate of North Division High School. He discusses his run for the school board in 1972, his activities with Organization of Organizations (Triple O) which he joined in 1975, the goals of Blacks for Two-Way Integration, problems with Superintendant McMurrin's desegregation plan, and the activities of the Coalitions for Peaceful Schools and to Save North Division.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 76)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Waiss, Beatrice J.
    Beatrice Weiss came to Milwaukee in 1967 and was a co-founder of the McKissick Community School. Her interview topics include the creation of the McKissick Community School, her children's experiences in Milwaukee Public Schools (MPS), and a comparison of MPS and Milwaukee Choice Schools. Waiss also gives an analysis of the rise and decline of Milwaukee's education reform movement.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 66-67)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Walker, Rev. Lucius
    Reverend Lucius Walker came to Milwaukee in the late 1950's. He was the first youth director for the Milwaukee Christian Center on Milwaukee's south side and was the founding director of Northcott Neighborhood House. His interview topics include the use of integration as a means for African Americans to access Milwaukee's educational resources. He also talks about Northcott Neighborhood House and the role it played in community development, including its role in the Organization of Organizations (Triple O).
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 68)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ward, Adolphus
    Adolphus Ward is former faculty member in the University of Wisconsin - Milwaukee's Theatre Department. Ward organized a parent conference in 1970 with the North Division Cluster to increase African American parent involvement in local schools. His interview topics include racial changes in the neighborhood of Center and 22nd streets, the difference in curriculum in predominately African American schools in 1960's, and his decision to send his children to Freedom Schools in 1964. He also talks about Organization of Organizations (Triple O) and its influence on community organization in Milwaukee in the 1960's.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 69)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Watkins, Ivory, and Linda Watkins Jefferson
    Linda (Watkins) Jefferson was the original plaintiff in the Barbee School desegregation case. Ivory Watkins is her mother. Linda is the major interviewee and discusses how she became involved in the legal case, the 1964 school boycott, testifying in court, civil rights activities while at Rufus King High School, her children's school experience, and Ivory's civil rights activities.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 70)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Williams, Evelyn Lockhart, and Ralph Williams Jr.
    Evelyn and Ralph Williams, both Milwaukee natives, discuss the 1964 Freedom School boycott, the Coalition to Save North Division, Howard Fuller, problems with the school board during the 1970's, the relationship between the Milwaukee Urban League and the Coalition, and involvement with the New North Division District in 1988.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 71)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Williams, Annette Polly
    Annette Polly Williams graduated from North Division High School and attended both Milwaukee Area Technical College and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. She was elected to the Wisconsin State Assembly in 1981 and served until 2011. Her interview topics include her participation as a parent on the board of the Urban Day School which offered Montessori education to African American children, racism her children experienced as students at Riverside High School, her work with the coalition to Save North Division High School, and the political climate in Milwaukee's African American community in the early 1970's.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 77)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wray, Jessie E.
    Jessie Wray served as treasurer for Organization of Organizations (Triple O). Triple O used non-violent protest to promote social change in the late 1960's. Wray's interview topics include The Federation of Independent Schools, Parents for Educational Progress, marching with Dick Gregory, and working with Milwaukee United School Integration Committee in the mid-1960's.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 72)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Wynn, Lauri
    Lauri Wynn was a teacher in the Milwaukee Public School district starting in the 1960's. She discussed her work with the Board of Governmental Operations, the planning and implementation of the Interrelated Language Skills Center, her work with the United Community Action Group, and her children's experience in schools during the 1960's and 1970's.
    - Interview, 1995, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 73-74)
    - Transcript, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Young, Ruby
    Ruby Young discusses substitute teaching in the Milwaukee Public School (MPS) system in the 1940's and 1950's, her journey in MPS to becoming a full time teacher as a married woman, and being an MPS elementary school teacher during the 1960's.
    - Interview, 1996, Audio cassette (Box 8, Audio 75)
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 2. Research Files, 1939-2004
  Series contains commission reports and transcripts on school desegregation and government housing; correspondence; leaflets and pamphlets produced by Committee of One Hundred, People United for Integration, and Triple O-Blacks For Two-Way Integration; and newspaper clippings.
  The collection case file includes electronic copies of project background files and transcripts; it is available for research use on request.
  - Administrative Change in Milwaukee Municipal Government, Thesis, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Barbee, Lloyd, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Beckley, Griselda, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Black Catholic, St. Benedict Parish, 1946, 1967, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Black Catholic, St. Elizabeth Parish, 1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Coggs, Marcia, and Isaac, 1973, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Committee of One Hundred, 1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Farrell, Walter, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Givens, John, 1971, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Golightly, Cornelius, 1956, 1963, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Halyard, Ardie, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Holt, Cornelius, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Kelley, William, 1939, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Learning from the Past-Lessons for the Future, Conference Report, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Lindsay, Bernice, 1969, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Malone, Carole, 1976, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Metro Integration Research Center, 1976, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Milwaukee Community Journal, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Morheuser, Marilyn, 1966, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - New North Division District, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Parrish, Clarence, 1962, 1967-1968, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Perlaus, E'Allyne, 1965, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Pitts, Terrance, and Orville, 1968, 1972, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - People United For Integration, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Project Background, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Relationship Between School Desegregation and Government Housing Program Report, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scott, Sarah, 1972, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Smyth, Edward, 1966, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Starms, Frances and Robert, 1973, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Triple O-Blacks for Two-Way Integration, 1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Wisconsin Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wisconsin Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights, Transcripts, May 22, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Wisconsin Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights, Transcripts, May 23, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)